Hola,
Todo el mundo. Bienvenidos. Es el 26 de septiembre.
2023. Estamos aquí dando inicio
Una nueva serie en streaming en “Active”.
Inferencia Instituto. Esto es la forma.
Transmisión 1.1. Hoy tenemos a David.
Cappel y también esta sección y
Transmisiones facilitadas por Sarah Ham. Nosotros.
Voy a tener una visión general, primero
Presentado por Sarah. Luego David.
Compartiré algo de trabajo sobre neuromórfico.
informática, y luego tendremos algo de tiempo
para discutir. Gracias a ambos por
Unirse y Sarah, para ti por primera vez.
presentación y también para introducir
sé de ti, si lo deseas. Sí, eso es un
Buena idea. Muchas gracias, Daniel.
Así que mi nombre es Sarah. Soy una
neurólogo especializado
inteligencia, actualmente trabajando en
campo de computación neuromórfica en
Instituto de Inferencia Activa en el Reino Unido. Así que voy.
para darte una visión general de alto nivel
¿qué es la computación neuromórfica antes de que
Escucha la emocionante charla de David en el primero.
Edición de esta nueva serie. Solo para avisar.
sabes, si estás viendo en Doble
En el futuro, hablo bastante rápido.
así que quizás no quieras verme en
Doble tiempo. Así que este código QR que puse
aquí le llevará a un artículo que yo
el pensamiento fue una muy buena introducción
al campo. Pero la computación neuromórfica
se pueden definir como sistemas de computación que
están diseñados para imitar la estructura y
función del sistema nervioso. Así
no tiene que ser el sistema nervioso humano
El sistema. El campo realmente toma
inspiración de todo tipo de animales
y los insectos, aunque las definiciones
no necesariamente implican reconocimiento
eso. algunas personas son bastante abiertas con
¿qué constituye neuromórfico, mientras tanto?
quizás otros preferirían neuromórfico
fue reservado para instancias de hardware
de neuronas biológicas como
a veces referido como no von Neumann
Active Inference Institute”, “Active Inference”, “pymdp”, “Youtube”, “YouTube”, “Discord”, “GitHub”, “ActiveInferenceInstitute”, “ActiveInference”. Los ordenadores. Y creo que eso es lo que...
el artículo al que se refiere ese código QR
su definición. Así que lo que creo es
realmente interesante es un poco de
el contexto. Así que, como nuestro actual von
La arquitectura de computadora Newman también
inspirado por la neurociencia, particularmente
el modelo de McCullough y Pitts 43.
inspirado por el primer borrador de Newman en
1945. Así que la neurociencia tiene una larga historia
de inspirar la ciencia de la computación y esto
también incluye aprendizaje por refuerzo
que se basa en teorías sobre
aprendizaje, toma de decisiones desde
Psicología conductual basada en recompensas
y castigos, y también Hebian
aprendizaje de los principios de las células que disparan
Juntos, conecta y conecta desde 49 se convirtió en
fundamentos para el aprendizaje no supervisado.
Así que, primero de todo, espera un segundo.
Para entender el porqué de
computación neuromórfica, realmente quería
para explicar lo que es tan genial sobre
Así que aquí hay algo de inspiración para
bombillas. Así que voy a preguntarte una
¿Pregunta. Solo quiero que pienses sobre.
hazlo por un segundo. En términos de luz
bombillas, ¿cuánta energía crees que la
¿El cerebro usa? ¿Crees que es más o?
menos energía que las bombillas iluminando el
¿La habitación en la que estás? Si estás en la
El futuro, por favor, detén esto. Pausa
Si quieres hacer algo en profundidad.
Cálculos. Pero voy a saltar directamente a
la respuesta. La respuesta está aquí.
en el círculo rosado. Así que son 20 vatios.
Así que eso es lo equivalente a una moderna actual.
lámpara de luz eficiente energéticamente para el día. Así.
Eso probablemente es lo que hay encima de mí ahora.
básicamente en mi habitación aquí. Este código QR
deberían llevarte a algo bastante interesante
Artículo sobre el consumo de energía en el cerebro.
Si te interesa eso, así que.
se necesitan unas cuatro plátanos al día para
Potencia tu cerebro. Y esto es
calculado, por cierto, basado en calorías
La información que el cerebro necesita. Así que, para
el contexto, el superordenador más rápido en
Europa, creo que se llama lumi, en
Finland ha sido llamado excepcionalmente
verde y su consumo de energía es de 8.5
un millón de vatios. Así que eso es alrededor de la mitad".
millones de bombillas, mientras tu cerebro
usa solo uno. Entonces la pregunta es,
Bueno, ¿qué hace tu cerebro con eso?
¿una bombilla o cuatro plátanos?
Aparentemente hace 1 billón de veces.
Cálculos por segundo. Así que hay muchos.
de otras estimaciones masivas que existen.
Esto no era ni siquiera el más grande por varios
órdenes de magnitud. Las estimaciones son
obviamente muy especulativo, pero ellos son
todo enorme y tienden a serlo todo
Basado en el número de neuronas, los suyos.
conexiones y tasas de disparo. Pero yo
piensa que es realmente importante para
el contexto que los supercomputadoras no pueden
de hecho, aún coinciden con nuestra complejidad de
habilidades o la adaptabilidad humana
El cerebro. Así que realmente sobresalimos mucho más allá
Supercomputadoras cuando se trata de cosas
como toma de decisiones complejas, aprendizaje
de la experiencia. Así que ¿cómo?
¿tu cerebro se compara con la IA? Así que, yo
mencionó que la IA moderna ya
inspirado por el cerebro. Sin embargo, artificial
los neurones son muy simplificados. Ellos
no captures la complejidad de
neuronas o redes biológicas, como,
ni siquiera cerca. Neuronas individuales son
en realidad más como redes en sí mismas.
Y la investigación sugiere que se modele uno.
el neurona biológico requiere un cinco a
red neuronal artificial de ocho capas profundas
red formada por alrededor de 1000 artificiales
neuronas. Este código QR debería llevarte a
el artículo. Por eso.
Tienes 86 mil millones de neuronas en tu
cerebro. Ellos trabajan juntos para formar un
eficiente en energía y baja latencia
Supercomputadora que funciona justo por encima de la temperatura ambiente.
temperatura, equivalente de aproximadamente
cuatro plátanos al día. Así espero que haya
dado que te da una sensación de lo increíble tu
el cerebro es como si no lo supieras
ya, y cómo ya ha sido utilizado
para inspirar, supongo, el IA bastante básico
lo que tenemos ahora comparado con el humano
inteligencia. Así que luego voy a
Explique las características clave del cerebro.
se están implementando para catalizar las nuestras
próxima generación de IA y tecnología
a través del campo de la neuromorfa
el cálculo, por eso todos están aquí.
Así que, el volumen tradicional y las computadoras
tienen ordenadores físicamente separados y
Unidades de memoria, mostradas aquí en el lado izquierdo.
Durante el cálculo, los datos deben transferirse.
hacia atrás y hacia adelante, como de verdad
Rápido. Así que hay un cuello de botella.
esencialmente para velocidad y energía
donde en las arquitecturas neuromórficas,
que se muestran aquí a la derecha, con
la ayuda de Dali, computación y memoria
ocurren en el mismo lugar. Así dicen.
para estar ubicados. Esencialmente,
Los neurones individuales realizan cálculo.
mientras la memoria es representada por el
la fuerza de las conexiones, los pesos
Entre neuronas. Así que las sinapsis. Así.
Es posible que patatas fritas como estas se crean con
componentes como Memoristas, por ejemplo
que puede emular pesos sinápticos y además.
esta arquitectura mejora la velocidad, es
reduce el consumo de energía. Y ¿qué es
es realmente interesante que permite
procesamiento paralelo masivo significado
que se pueden abordar múltiples problemas
al mismo tiempo. Así que esto es
particularmente importante, esto
arquitectura para diversos casos de uso
pero también porque al llegar al final
La Ley de Moore, que es el número de
transistores que pudisteis físicamente
hazlo cada vez más pequeño para que quepa en un chip.
Y es importante también porque la humanidad
debe reducir drásticamente su energía
consumiendo contra el telón de caída de
creando cada vez más IA poderosa.
Las neuronas artificiales suelen utilizar
activación continua mostrada en el lado izquierdo
están siempre activos, mientras neuromórfico
los neurones, se dice que están disparando, así
son o no lo son, que es
mostrado aquí a la derecha. Así como.
algo como un potencial de acción. Así que la
los beneficios de esto son nuevamente poder,
eficiencia y también aplicaciones donde
El momento es importante y esto se da.
que son impulsados por eventos. Así
esencialmente tienen el potencial de
dimensiones espaciales y temporales que
entonces habilita espacial y temporal adicionales
codificación y procesamiento de información.
Quizás te estés preguntando un poco por las GPU.
que también permiten el procesamiento paralelo.
La investigación sugiere que las GPU son adecuadas.
Arquitecturas para el despliegue de potenciales espiking
redes neuronales que creo hacen esto
un momento realmente interesante para el campo
dado lo alto que están subiendo las tarjetas gráficas
más y más extendido.
El cerebro aprende la fuerza de las sinapsis
Entre neuronas. Esto se basa en pre
y los patrones de disparo sináptico. Creo.
La charla de David hablará mucho, iremos.
profundizar en esto. Pero ahí
hay muchos tipos y patrones diferentes de
esto a través del cerebro dependiendo de la
tipos de sinapsis como las sinapsis excitatorias
inhibitorio, excitatorio a excitatorio
Y el campo neuromórfico está trabajando para
aprovechar estas reglas debido a los beneficios
para aprendizaje en chip y también
aplicaciones como el reconocimiento de patrones
y el computo en el borde también.
el cálculo siendo un caso de uso bastante grande
por la computación neuromórfica debido
la especie de naturaleza impulsada por eventos y también
el bajo consumo de energía. Y este código QR
deberían llevarte a algo bastante interesante
Artículo sobre STDP que encontré.
¿Qué soluciones neuromórficas son?
¿Está disponible? ¿Ahora? Quizás solo pienses.
esto es todo teórico, hay
realmente muchas soluciones diferentes
donde te daré realmente
Resumen general de. Así el Humano
El proyecto Cerebro ha creado varias grandes
Escalar computadoras neuromórficas incluyendo
Spinnaker, que este aquí en
la base de esta tabla, como tal vez como
el tamaño de mi cara o algo así. Así.
que se ejecuta en tiempo real y es
compuesta por múltiples de uso general
diseñan y fabrican microprocesadores y también
BrainScaleS que es acelerado
Arquitectura análoga y se ejecuta 1000
veces en tiempo real. Así que
el tablero al lado del azul, es un
versión de tamaño de tarjeta de crédito actual
BrainScaleS, que han estado
hecho, lo cual pensé que era bastante genial.
Y también hay algunos actores importantes
en el espacio. Así que este azul aquí es
Active Inference Institute” están al tanto de “Active Inference”, “pymdp”, “Youtube”, “YouTube”, “Discord”, “GitHub”, “ActiveInferenceInstitute”, “ActiveInference” y el chip de Intel de Louihi.
Dos. Ahora, eso es su Inferencia Neurormótica.
chip, y tienen una de código abierto
un marco de software para eso también
porque realmente quieren catalizar el
comunidad de código abierto para involucrarse
con ello. Así también los sensores neuromórficos
¿existe? Así que esta pequeña cosa azul en el
el medio es en realidad una neuromórfico
La cámara. Quizás sea así de grande. Así
buscan recrear cómo nuestro sistema nervioso
El sistema percibe estímulos como la luz.
Así que, por ejemplo, en un Instituto de Inferencia Activa
cámara, que es la que está aquí, cada una
pixel trabaja de forma independiente con un
resolución de microsegundos. Espero que mi
Un GIF funcionará. Ahí lo tienes. Así que puedes
ve cada píxel trabajando allí, que es
Qué interesante. Así que en comparación con la tradicional
Las cámaras digitales, han mejorado.
rendimiento con movimiento y menor consumo de energía
El consumo. También hubo un
El neuromórfico reciente de Intel,
que fue bastante interesante. Así que podía aprender
el aroma de un químico después de solo uno
exposición, y luego podría identificar
ese olor incluso cuando estaba enmascarado por
Otros. Y entonces finalmente, esto es una
Un robot humanoide llamado un ICup. Y qué
puedes hacer es que puedes realmente integrar
Sensores neuromórficos, como los
cámara, y luego chips neuromórficos
quizás Spinnaker o Brain Scales en un
dispositivo humanoide como este u otro
dispositivos como un dron. Y luego de
que puedes realmente crear algo encarnado
Sistemas neuromorfo. Y esto es
algo en lo que trabajamos en Smart
Laboratorio de Tecnologías Interactivas en
Sheffield en el Reino Unido.
Esta diapositiva simplemente destaca algunos de los
Aplicaciones potenciales de la neuromorfa
informática, que pensé que eran bastante
interesante cuando se piensa en ello, así.
la comprensión del contexto, patrón
reconocimiento, detección avanzada, fusión
aprendizaje, generalización en tareas
toma de decisiones compleja
explicabilidad y interfaces cerebrales
Así que todas estas habilidades son realmente
es beneficioso cuando estás pensando sobre
aplicaciones centradas en el ser humano y en tiempo real
en entornos dinámicos. Así como cosas como
coches autónomos, por ejemplo, y
personalmente, creo que la inferencia neuromórfica
los sistemas también probablemente serán el futuro
Substrato de interfaces cerebro-ordenador.
Probablemente un poco sesgado porque soy un.
neurólogo, pero están con poca energía
son en tiempo real y también tienen
arquitecturas que coincidan con las nuestras
El hardware. Así que creo que pronto veremos
el campo del BCI siendo catalizado por
sistemas neuromorfos, particularmente quizás
para híbridos de hardware y bioweave. Así
quizás incluso potencialmente conteniendo
las propias células cerebrales de las personas, que puedes
realmente crece solo de una célula ciliada.
Y un enfoque particular de nuestro trabajo es
diseñando IA que aprende de manera similar
un camino hacia un humano. Así que tiene una innata
Sentido de curiosidad y aprende.
a través de la interacción con el mundo real.
Así que en los años 50, Alan Turing dijo,
en lugar de intentar producir un programa
para simular la mente adulta, ¿por qué no?
preferir intentar producir uno que
Simula el cerebro del niño. Si esto
fueron entonces sometidos a un apropiado
curso de educación, se obtendría
el cerebro adulto. Esto es muy mucho el
Filosofía detrás del desarrollo neurológico
Enfoque en IA y neuromórfico
la computación, que solo quería
Resalta. Hay algunos
desafíos en el campo. Estos son muy
de alto nivel, pero solo te daré una
una pequeña idea de ello, así.
El entrenamiento de redes neuronales espiking es más
más compleja que la red neuronal tradicional
redes. También diseñando hardware que
realmente implementa redes neuronales espiking
redes STDP a gran escala se dice
ser bastante desafiante y luego también
desarrollando algoritmos que realmente puedan
utilizar eficazmente todo esto
tecnologías. Así que el hardware, el STDP,
es un área de investigación activa en curso.
Si estás aquí, probablemente...
interesado en Active Inference. Así que yo
Quería destacar esto. De hecho,
alguien puso en el Discord hoy uno de
estos estudios, que estuvieron bastante interesantes.
Así, algunos estudios recientes han...
combinado computación neuromórfica con
principios de inferencia activa. Así.
Active Inference" proviene de
neurociencia, y yo argumentaría que
se adapta muy bien a la neuromorfa
arquitecturas. En un reciente artículo sobre
inteligencia neuromórfica incorporada, así.
no realmente mencionó “Active Inference
Inferencia en IT. El código QR en la parte superior.
Aquí se sugirió que una verdadera
Avance en neuromorfología que…
¿Qué pasa si todo el diseño del sistema es?
Basado en la computación biológica
principios con una interacción apretada
entre la estimación de
los alrededores y el estado propio del robot
y la toma de decisiones, planificación y
acción. Así que algunos de esos temas podrían
suenan bastante familiares a la gente
interesado en Active Inference y yo
sugeriría que Active Inference es
bien situado para cumplir con estos requisitos.
Y solo quería destacar un par.
de estudios recientes aquí. Así que este sobre
el izquierdo, Gandalfiatal, recientemente
demostró plasticidad y rápido
aprendizaje no supervisado en un neuromórfico
Sistema usando Active Inference
los principios. El autor sugirió que
sus experimentos podrían ser adoptados para
Implementa un cerebro como predictivo
Capacidades en robótica neuromorfa
Sistemas. Y luego estaba el Plato.
papel cerebral, que algunos de ustedes pueden ser
Familiarizado por Kaganatal. Así que esto fue.
un híbrido de hardware neuromórfico biológico
el sistema que los autores afirmaron que era
el cuerpo. El sistema mostró un rápido
aparente aprendizaje del juego de Pong
utilizando el principio de energía libre para
Aprendiendo. Y los autores afirmaron que
el sistema exhibió sintético
inteligencia biológica. Así que el campo
Implementando principios de inferencia activa
en sistemas neuromórficos es muy incipiente.
Y la idea detrás de este flujo más...
la serie es para crear un espacio y una
comunidad para compartir conocimientos, ideas y
experteza para catalizar el campo. Creo
saltos tecnológicos realmente emocionantes
probablemente vendrán de esto
Así que gracias por escuchar mi
repaso rápido de inferencia neuromórfica 101.
Vamos a escuchar ahora mismo
De David. Así que David, tú al micrófono. Si
quieres presentarte, por favor.
Gracias, Sarah.
Compartiría mi pantalla.
Sí.
¿Puedes ver ahora mi pantalla?
la presentación sí. Ok, perfecto.
De acuerdo. Hola. Me llamo David Kappel.
Soy un investigador y líder de grupo en
Instituto para la Informática de Moyo en el
Universidad Rural Bohom. Así que yo
liderando al grupo en materia de máquinas sostenibles
aprendizaje y tenemos un enfoque muy fuerte
sobre computación neuromórfica. Por eso
Estoy aquí hoy y voy a empezar.
con una motivación muy similar a
Sarah lo hizo, lo cual fue realmente genial".
La inspiración para esta charla, creo.
probablemente la mayoría de ustedes lo han visto
resultado reciente interesante, y no
Significa Alemania ganando el baloncesto.
campeonato, pero este gran salto
en inteligencia artificial que hemos.
ha sido visto en los últimos años, especialmente
los últimos dos o tres años. Así que esto es un
imagen generada a partir de un texto por un
Red de Dali y es realmente asombroso.
Se consideraba ciencia ficción como.
hace apenas dos o tres años. Y esto fue
esencialmente hecho posible por un
Enfoque neuromórfico, que es profundo.
redes neuronales. Y estas redes neuronales profundas.
las redes se han vuelto enormes ahora, pero esto
También viene con una advertencia. Así que básicamente
el lado opuesto es que entre otras
Los problemas que podrían tener estos modelos,
consumen enormes cantidades de energía.
Así modelos como Dali o Jet GPT,
como ya mencionó Sarah, ellos
consumen presupuestos de energía que son
comparable a casas o coches, así.
Entrenar a Chat GPT una sola vez es como
un gigavatio-hora aproximadamente, así que
serían 300 toneladas de emisión de CO2
y muchas veces, lo que llega es a muchos
el tiempo de vida útil de un automóvil típico
Así que esto viene con dos problemas.
Obviamente, esto hace que entrenar estos sea…
modeles solo accesibles a un grupo muy pequeño
Número de jugadores muy grandes. Así.
esencialmente las grandes compañías tecnológicas y
segundo, y quizás incluso más
importantly, this is not compatible with" se traduce como "importante, esto no es compatible con".
un planeta con recursos limitados. Así si
El crecimiento de la IA continúa como si fuera así.
ha consumido en los últimos años
El 13% del consumo energético mundial por
2030 y básicamente superará eso.
el sector de transporte en otro
aproximadamente cinco años. Así que esto plantea el
¿pregunta, ¿es sostenible la máquina?
¿está aprendiendo en absoluto? Y obviamente,
ya que estoy trabajando en el grupo de
aprendizaje automático sostenible, creo
Sí, y por qué creo yo.
es porque sabemos un sistema que es
muy eficiente y probablemente todavía
mejores que estos modelos de IA, que es
el cerebro humano, que consume, como
Sarah mencionó, alrededor de 20 vatios o
cuatro plátanos al día.
Es muchas órdenes de magnitud más
más eficiente que los modelos de IA que tenemos
hoy. Pero hasta ahora no.
saben esencialmente cómo funcionan estas redes
y especialmente cómo entrenarlos. Y
básicamente nuestro objetivo es transferir ahora
Mecanismos del aprendizaje automático. Nosotros.
tengan esta bonita imagen aquí. básicamente
empezamos desde el lado del aprendizaje automático
donde ya sabemos cómo movernos.
Así tenemos estos modelos que son
asombroso y eso nos da realmente
resultados impresionantes, pero no lo son
eficientes y queremos transferirlos
a una nueva generación de IA eficiente.
Y nuestra idea es usar inspiración de
neurociencia que hace esto
transfiere más rápido y es posible en
primera posición. ¿Vale?
Actualmente, la biología es una gran fuente de
La inspiración y siempre vuelve.
esquina con resultados muy sorprendentes.
Y uno de estos resultados que encontré por casualidad
hace un par de años fue eso
fiabilidad de los sinapsis en
el cerebro. Así que, como probablemente ya sabrán,
los neurones de tu cerebro están conectados para
sinapsis. Pero si mira
este es un artículo de 2019 y ellos
podría identificar individualmente
sinapsis y podrían desencadenarlas
realiza una liberación sináptica, como una sola
transmisión. Pero si observa estos
mediciones, se ve que esto es
realmente cubierto de ruido. Así que esencialmente,
si básicamente promedias esto y
acercar para ver aquí estas
rasgajos sinápticos típicos, que es la
La línea blanca promedio aquí. Pero por debajo de ella.
ves este gran temblor. Así que realmente
suben varios desvíos estándar
y hacia abajo. Y esto es realmente
sorprendente considerando que las neuronas son
probablemente la célula más costosa de todas
Introduce tu cuerpo en términos de energía
consumen. Están realmente en
comparación, consumen bastante
de energía en tu cuerpo. Así que tú
espera que estas transmisiones que son
comunicándose entre neuronas, que son
muy costoso, debería ser muy fiable.
Así que esto es muy contraintuitivo estas
resultados y ha estado desconcertando
neurocientíficos durante bastante tiempo.
Y entonces ahí
es una segunda observación desconcertante,
que es esa la morfología
de neuronas se parece un poco a esto, así.
esto sería tu típica pirámide
neuron tienes en tu corteza.
Pero usted ve que esto es en realidad, para un
célula, bastante grande y alargada.
Así que esto puede llegar hasta un milímetro en
el cerebro humano, lo que significa que si un
la sinapsis se dispara en alguna parte aquí, tiene un
tiene mucho difícil comunicándose con
Cuerpo celular, que está aquí abajo. Así que la
señales eléctricas que se producen
aquí pueden viajar hacia abajo aquí
pero la sinapsis aquí arriba no tiene manera de
medir los voltajes reales en las
cuerpo celular. Y esto es en realidad el
un lugar interesante porque aquí hay...
potenciales de acción formados. Así que si el
synapse le gustaría saber sobre
¿Qué está pasando en el cuerpo celular así?
puede hacer predicciones sobre cómo
el neurona se comportará y cómo lo
Interactúa con el mundo. Y esto es
otro muy desconcertante o
problema abierto en neurociencia, ¿cómo esto
la comunicación realmente sale bien
neuronas individuales entre el cuerpo celular y
Los SynOps. Se sabe que realmente
los potenciales de acción pueden viajar hacia atrás
arriba. Así que ven algo binario.
cuando el neurona dispara,
pero no pueden medir realmente la
potencial de membrana abajo aquí. Así que solo
las señales eléctricas más prominentes
puede realmente retropropagar a través de
Esto y esto sugiere
que la sinapsis realmente tiene
información dispersa sobre lo que está pasando
en el cuerpo celular. Y más
Los modelos de plasticidad sináptica no.
cubrir esto en absoluto y nos preguntábamos
¿cómo funciona esta interacción? ¿Cómo podemos
la sinapsis producen útiles
señales de aprendizaje dada esta escasez
información sobre este estado importante
¿del neurona? Y nuestra idea era que
esencialmente estas dos observaciones,
Estos altos niveles de ruido y la
sinapsis y esta gran distancia entre
cuerpo celular y sinapsis que dan esto
altas incertidumbres, estos son realmente
los dos lados de la misma moneda. Así que nuestros
la hipótesis era que realmente podíamos
utiliza los mismos modelos que
sabemos ya del comportamiento
nivel, cómo un agente puede
actúa y realiza en un entorno de
alta incertidumbre. Y simplemente aplicamos esto
A cada registro hay un error.
Así que cada registro debería utilizar esto
mismos modelos, básicamente.
Y este modelo sugeriría inmediatamente
eso realmente transmisiones sinápticas
deberían ser ruidosas y estos niveles de
el ruido expresaría incertidumbre sobre
el entorno. Y luego podemos usar
para derivar reglas de aprendizaje y
podemos compararlos uno al lado del otro para
Biología. Y esta es lo primero que...
Quiero mostrarte. Así que simplemente doy una muy
Introducción rápida al principio de energía libre
modelo, ya que algunos de ustedes quizás no lo estén
que está familiarizado con ello, pero esto es
esencialmente un modelo para describir
una situación como esta. tienes una persona
eso es interactuando con algunos
entorno y aquí asumí muy
Tan simple. Así que esta persona intenta lanzar
lanzar una pelota a un objetivo. Y nosotros como humanos,
somos buenos resolviendo tareas así, y
También somos buenos resolviendo tareas así.
si hay altos niveles de incertidumbre
en esto. Así que si la persona puede recibir
alguna retroalimentación visual, pero gran parte de esto
El feedback puede estar oculto. Así que puedes
imagina esto pasando tras una pared.
Y la persona todavía podría querer...
predice la trayectoria de esto
una pelota volando hacia el objetivo para que
puede generar una acción precisa.
Así asignaremos algunas variables a
Estos estados aquí. Así que tenemos
esencialmente este comentario que este
la persona puede observar y tenemos esto
unobserved state of the ball flying
here, which we call U, where the person
doesn't have direct access to it, would
only see parts of it, for example, when
the ball is at the corners of the ball
appearing. And then to model
this essentially, or to describe this
behavior, the person would have
an internal description of this
trajectory. So an internal model of this
state, U. And this
model would then be updated to match the
observed feedback.
And this can be described very nicely in
this beautiful mathematical framework of
the free energy principle. So the idea
is that you would essentially establish
a model of your internal state, so
essentially how the internal
states and the state of the environment
interact. And you would have a model of
the feedback, so how the states and the
feedback you observe interact. And
essentially you can then write down a
loss function that measures the distance
between this model of the internal state
and this model of the feedback and the
external state.
And then by essentially
minimizing this distance between the
two, you can derive all sorts of
behaviorally relevant,
can solve behaviorally relevant
problems, for example, learning. But you
can also use this for other things,
like figuring out what are good actions,
for example. So making inference about
both the internal states and the
actions. For example, and this is in a
nutshell, the free energy principle.
And this object here happens to be what
is known as the variation of free
energy, which is also just coincides
with statistical physics. And this is
where this framework has its name from.
But you see that all is probabilistic
here. So essentially you have two
probability functions q for the internal
model and P for this interaction between
states and observations. And you have
here a distance measure between them
that you want to minimize. So now if we
look at the neuron and the synapse and
how they interact with each other, we
find a very similar picture. So single
SynOps, which we have here in green,
has an internal state which we,
for simplicity, model only as the
synaptic weight. Based on this, the
SynOps, when it's triggered by a
presynaptic spike, it would generate a
post synaptic current. This would then
propagate to the soma, which is our
external state, which we cannot directly
observe because it's too far away from
the synapse. But we can see a feedback,
which is this back propagating action
potential, which is this binary variable
that tells us whether the neuron has
spiked or not. So this is exactly the
same framework if we write it down like
that. And we can just use the same
mathematics to solve it.
So to solve it, we only have to come up
with a couple of we have to make a
couple of assumptions. So we have to
write down a model for this guy here.
So this model of how the feedback
and the external state interact. But we
have very good models for this. This has
been studied over many years. So here
you see how typically a model neuron
behaves. So you have here the membrane
potential of a leaky integrated fire
neuron. And you see that this is just
going up and down. So this neuron would
receive a lot of presynaptic input and
maybe also noise. And eventually at some
point it hits a threshold, it would
generate a spike. So that would be the
sets that travels to the downstream
neurons and also back to the SynOps.
And then it resets,
right?
So we can write this down mathematically
as a very simple differential equation.
But the neuron doesn't have access to
this state again. So it's again behind
this wall, it only sees these spike
events. But we can actually, for this
simple case of a leaky integrated fire
neuron, we can solve this analytically.
So we can write down what is the
posterior distribution of membrane
potentials given the spike times. And
what comes out of this is actually a so
called stochastic bridge model, or in
this case of a leak integrated in fire
neuron. It's an orange bridge model. So
this can be written down analytically.
It's not simple, but it's doable.
And we can then just use this directly.
So this model that we have to again
write down these free energy
functionals. So we make here an
assumption how the synapse actually
produces post synoptic currents and how
they are integrated in the neuron. But
that's also given by the leaky
integrated fire neuron and actually the
stochastic inputs that the synapse
generates. So for simplicity, we only
assume here basically Gaussian synapses
that would inject draw a Gaussian random
variable and inject this to a leaky
integrated fire neuron. And then all
these ingredients actually can be solved
in closed form and we can derive
learning rules that would minimize this
free energy functional. Now,
and if we do that,
this has a bunch of nice properties
because this Einstein Beck bridge is
completely determined by the back
propagating action potentials. So
basically the times of the post synaptic
spikes that arrive at the neuron,
this shape that we get here only depends
on two neighboring post synaptic spikes,
which means that we get here
automatically a learning rule that looks
like this. So a learning rule that only
depends on the difference between two
postal optic spikes, which we call here
delta t two, and the
difference between the post synoptic
spike and the actual input that is
triggered at some point on the
presynaptic side. And we can
basically make here this lookup table
and just compute what would be the
update that these sign ups would need to
make so that it learns optimally in
terms of this free energy principle.
And this is the shape that we get out.
You see that there is a strong
dependence on the post synoptic firing
rate, but there is also a dependence on
basically this typical STDP that Sarah
mentioned before, what is the relative
positioning of the pre and postsynoptic
spike. So in a nutshell, this model
can now be split into essentially two
pathways. So we have this ATOC response,
which basically just whenever there is a
presynaptic spike that triggers an
action in the synapse, we would draw
from this Gaussian distribution and
inject it into the neuron.
And then there is this postalk update
where the synapse would look up in this
onstain Woolenbeck bridge, what would
have been the optimal output that it
should have generated, so what would
have been the optimal action. And then
it compares the actual action with this
optimal action according to this free
energy principle and then generates a
delayed response which is an update of
the synaptic weight. Okay?
And importantly, this internal model is
only implicit. It's encoded, so to say,
into this spike time dependent.
Plasticity rule. So how
do these rules then look and how do they
compare to biology? And actually the fit
is quite nicely given that this is
derived really from first principles
without making any assumptions. So this
is the measurement in biology. This is
this B and Al rule, b and Pool,
very old work where they actually did
this in vitro studies where they
injected pre and post synaptic spikes
and then they measured what is the
weight change in the synopsis. And this
is the rule that is predicted by our
model. And you see that at least in a
first order approximation, it gives us
very similar shapes. And this also makes
sense because the
synapse wants to change the most when
it's close to
the pre and post synoptic spike times
because this is where or the post
synoptic spike times because this is
where it knows the most about the state
of the postynaptic neuron. The free
energy principle would actually suggest
these kind of cones with
almost no assumption essentially. But we
also get because we have not just the
first order spike time dependent
plasticity rule, but we also have this
dependency on the post not of the firing
rate. We can also compare this to other
results. And this here is this old work
by Kaupner and Brunel. So this is
actually a model, but that was very
detailed describing the
plasticity based on the pre and post
synoptic firing rate in the synapse.
And this is what our model predicts. So
if we inject render and pre and post
synaptic bossBack trains with different
rates, our model would predict this
shape, which again is not a perfect
match. But given that this is a very
idealistic model, it's actually the main
features that low firing rates on
the postynopstic side would lead to
depression and higher to potentiation
are reflected in this.
Okay, I assume I still have ten minutes,
right? Okay, so I would give
a quick intermediate summary and then I
want to show some other work where we
actually apply this now to
actual machine learning model.
So what we have seen here is that
synapses are actually are very
stochastic and this was a
big puzzle. And B suggests that actually
the synaptic noise is actually the
synapses way of reporting its own
uncertainty about the environment,
where the environment is actually the
post synaptic neuron and it really
interacts in this fashion of the free
energy principle with this post synaptic
neuron or that's a very nice way of
describing it. And if you're interested
more, there's a paper, a preprint out,
you can read up on all this.
Okay, so how does this now connect to
neuromorphics? And actually so we are
not actually doing neuromorphic
hardware, we are doing neuromorphic
algorithms. So we try to bring these
inspirations now into actual machine
learning models and we thought that this
might be a good attack angle to
solve a problem that is well known in
machine learning. So I just drew
here very simple convolutional neural
networks with various convolutional
layers and then maybe some dense layers
that you would have in your machine
learning algorithm. And the way this is
trained, as many of you know, I guess,
is through end to end errorback
propagation. So the idea is that you
have a training set which has inputs and
targets. So, for example, in a
classification task, this could be
pictures of cats and dogs. And you would
have targets which are class labels,
so to say. So there's actually
artificial neurons in there, and one of
these neuron may be active for cats and
1 may be active for dogs. And in your
training, that data, you have exactly
these labels that were generated by
humans, that were sitting down doing
this by hand. And then during training,
you show these examples to the network
by propagating these inputs all the way
from the input layer to the output
layer. Then the output is here compared
to these hand labeled targets. And then
the mismatch between the two is back
propagated through all these layers back
to the input. And all the weights or the
synoptic weights that are here in
between inside these layers would then
be updated accordingly, so that after
doing this many, many times, this
network becomes good in telling apart
Kelvin docs. So this has a problem,
this algorithm. It works great in
practice and it's the foundation of all
these models we have talked about, like
Dali or Jet GPT, but it is quite
inefficient. And the problem is what is
known in the literature as the locking
problem. So if you would split up this
network now into blocks, which I already
did before, but this is arbitrary, but
for implementing this efficiently in
terms of a software algorithm, it might
be interesting to do that. And now you
would want these blocks ideally to run
in parallel, so that you can basically
show the first example on this first
block and then already train it while
the second block is doing something
else. But this is not really possible
with end to end back propagation because
of this lock in problem, because the
activation of the second block depends
on the activation of the first block.
So you have to propagate it all the way
to the end. Then you compute this error
and you would then back propagate. And
only when this is done, you can start
the next epoch where you show a new
bunch of examples and
you see that during all this time,
here, the thread that would run this
first block maybe would be idle and has
to wait essentially all the time. And
this obviously makes them very
inefficient. And now our idea was that
we use basically what we had learned
from this earlier model on how synopsis
communicate over these long distances
through this free energy principle, and
also apply it just to a deep neural
network. And the idea is that you have
here, again, basically you have already
this generation of inputs to some
output. But what is missing to make it
applicable to the free energy principle
is this feedback that you always need.
The idea was that we put here a very
lightweight feedback network. So
essentially each of these blocks now in
this deep neural network would be
accompanied by a feedback block that
locally generates a target. So we used
here really in the simplest case, which
we have, so this is very recent work,
we only used linear blocks so far. So
these are single linear layers and we
would generate now these outputs here in
these feedback blocks and then use the
free energy principle to derive a
local loss. That allows us again to
minimize both these feedback weights
that we have here and also the weights
in the forward network. So it's
essentially the same idea. So we have
here these outputs which we interpret
now as parameters to a probability
function. So we can apply this
probabilistic framework, but now all the
rest basically rolls out the same way.
So we assume that these outputs are
essentially the internal states of this
model and we have these
observations given in the inputs and the
targets. And now we try to minimize
basically P would now be this feed
forward network and Q would be now a
function that contains features
of both the feedback and
the feed forward network. And the nice
thing is that if we I don't have time to
go into the details now, but if you
write this out, you see that this
actually decomposes, this lock term here
decomposes into local linear terms that
give you these local losses here. So
essentially that you can minimize here
block local between forward and the
corresponding feedback block, a loss
function. And you can then actually do
this in parallel because maybe the
picture is good to see here. So what you
have to do now you have a bit of
overhead because you have this feedback
block. So this would be the two
execution times of the feed forward
block and the feedback block. But in
principle they can run in parallel and
once the forward block is done, the next
forward block can start propagating
through this network, but simultaneously
already the forward block, because it
already received a target here, can
start updating the weights and when it's
done, it's free to operate on the next
epoch. So there is no locking anymore in
this framework. Okay, so I'm
pretty much done. I'm also out of time,
I think. So how does this perform? Of
course we changed the learning
algorithm. Now we have to also go back
and see if this is still giving
us the same performance.
As I said, this is the first results
we have here now and at least to mid
scale data sets like cipher
ten or so, this seems to actually
perform very well. So we attract it for
standard architectures, fashion MNIST
with ResNet 15 and ResNet 18. We worked
mostly so far for small data sets like
Fashion MNIST with applying free splits
to ResNet 50. We get basically the same
performance as standard backprop. As
networks get deeper, you see that our
problem that we have now is actually
overfitting because we have these local
targets. It seems that these smaller
blocks actually overfit to some extent.
This is not so severe for still up to
tasks like cipher ten. So we get quite
close already. But if you go now for
really large tasks, there's still
something missing for like
single splits. We are getting there,
but we are not reaching all the way up
to back propagation. But it's still
interesting to see that you can apply
this principle also to these standard
machine learning algorithms. Okay, this
is my second summary. So actually we
found that deep neural networks are
surprisingly good in generalizing over
probability spaces. This is how actually
this work started. And our
idea was to exploit this and to utilize
it to distribute learning in the same
fashion as in the first project I showed
you and to solve this credit assignment
problem by generating these feedback
networks.
Yeah, that's basically it. And then I
want to acknowledge my coworkers and my
students. So I have two very good PhD
students, carlisle and Cabrill, who is
now here in Bohom and works on this
topic. And the first project I showed
was work I did together when I was in
gettingham with Christian Tetlav. And
the second project is I worked closely
with Christian Meyer and Anand Sutomoni
and yeah, thank you.
Thank you very much, David. That was
absolutely fascinating. I think it's
incredible how closely the sort of model
matched biology. Like considering you
derived it from first principles, I
think that was really cool. I did have a
question just about the last sort of the
bit. You spoke about the Convolutional
network and you said traditionally it
has to go all the way end to end, which
is really inefficient. And then you
showed the results that you got. Did you
look at energy consumption with yours as
well? Not yet. So we are actually
currently working on it's
actually not so easy to implement these
things in standard machine learning
toolboxes. So Carlisle is currently
looking into this, the PhD student in
Jester, he has an implementation now,
and he's now evaluating how well
we can make use of this parallelization
in practice. But we are actually quite
confident that for
parallelizing it, it should be there.
The question is how much you save in
terms of energy. Because for these
smaller scale models that we use now,
ResNet 18, ResNet 50,
the effect might be not that huge. So
once we ramp this up to really larger
models, the effect should be bigger.
But yeah, this is ongoing work. Very
cool. Thank you. And then I was just
wondering as well, this local error back
propagation, is that something that
other people have tried with these
convolutional neural networks or is this
quite a new way of implementing it?
There is a bunch of approaches that do
this. For example, I mean, the closest I
guess is target propagation which has
been proposed, which essentially uses
random feedback weights to back
propagate here. So these guys would not
be trained.
And this
works nicely also for small scale
problems. But as far as I know, they
don't perform that well. Even for cipher
ten, it already starts breaking down
because these random feedback weights
are just too coarse an approximation, I
think. And this is the first okay,
maybe I have to be careful. I think this
is the first method that allows you to
train these feedback weights. That is
not a contrastive method. There is a
bunch of methods that use a contrastive
step. So you have
maybe seen this forward forward
algorithm and all these things,
but what they have to do always is they
send in the actual input data and then
they send an kind of anti input,
an anti input that is usually
generated artificially. So they do some
distortion to the input to make it and
then they have to use both information
locally to do the update. So the network
has to keep in memory the input and the
anti input and the responses. And this
makes these approaches a bit harder to
parallelize in this. And the nice thing
here is that we derive an
upper bound to this variational free
energy loss that can be spelled out
completely by forward propagation. And
that I think is new. So that is the new
bit of this. Very cool.
That's awesome.
Well, yeah, few comments, one piece that
kind of between the two of your talks.
That was at least a new distinction to
me, which was the difference between the
Neuromorphic hardware and the
Neuromorphic algorithms. So it's not
just about new hardware or Wetware,
though that would be great to see.
It's almost like there's this
intermediate or a bridge step with using
the algorithms on
the hardware we have today that
like Sarah mentioned, the Spiking neural
networks which are amenable to GPUs or
just using standardized CPU multicore
scheduling approaches. You can already
do more with what we have
using the Neuromorphic algorithms. So
it's not just a material science
topic, but also there's a lot
at the really micro scale that we can
learn related to noise processing
scheduling and then also even at higher
levels of abstraction, probably learning
from biomimicry and cognitive systems
more generally. But that was a
distinction for me.
Yeah. So maybe to add yeah. So I think
that the problem becomes really now more
pressing as these Neuromorphic devices
become so the hardware devices become
more mature and they usually cannot
really shine on these standard
machine learning algorithms because they
are really optimized for GPUs. So you
need to think a little bit. So you have
to take one step back and think again
about the algorithmic side to really
use them to full capacity. And as you
have seen now, we collaborate with
Professor Meyer, who is doing this
spinnaker chip in Dresden, but there's
also other approaches like the Louis
chip that Sarah mentioned from intel and
so on, and they are really looking
into this. Now, also from the
algorithmic side. I find
it really useful. It's kind of like a
mindset or a mental framework when I'm
thinking about computers or AI, and this
is probably because I'm a
neuroscientist, but I also have to
translate it to, well, how does the
brain work, how does the information
processing work, et cetera, in the
brain? And when I came to sort of
computer science and AI after
neuroscience, I found myself naturally
translating it. But I feel like the
framework is just a really useful way of
understanding computation at the end of
the day because our brains, as I said,
are just these massive supercomputers.
And I'm constantly reading papers on
computer science or whatever. And then
once you can conceptualize anything
really as well, how neuromorphic is
this? And then if you start thinking
about, well, how could you tweak it so
it's slightly more neuromorphic? And is
that then going to give you these gains
that we get with the brain? Is it going
to give you some extra parallel
computation or is it going to give you
some energy efficiency? So, yeah, I find
it the definitions when I was looking at
the definition is I think it really
depends who writes the definition. And
because it's such a dynamic area at the
moment as well, I think it has been
changing and it will be changing, but
for me, I feel like neuromorphic is more
of like a mental framework where I look
at things through conceptualize,
through yeah, I think it's. It'S also
not very well defined.
You also mentioned that actually
artificial neural networks are a
neuromorphic concept, if you want, and
they were from the first day. And it's
a big success story, right, if you look
into the 90s or so when these support
vector machines and these alternative
models came up, but none of them have
outlived the neuromorphic approaches.
So it's actually very nice. But still
there is this community that thinks that
there is more features from the brain
that you need to put in to get to
the real thing. So I think this is a bit
of a it's not a very well defined term,
actually, and I think with. Your
research, yours is almost like the
smallest level that I've seen people
look at it on. I don't know if you've
seen anything else, but we're not just
talking about a cell level of free
energy and active inference. We're
actually talking about a cell structure.
So then you think, well, how small does
it go? Are we going to talk about cell
subcellular structures eventually, like
Mitochondria using free energy in a
similar way with compartments, I guess
actually it'd be interesting to get your
thoughts, david on, you talked at the
start about how synapses are
compartmentalized. Do you see different
sort of instantiations of this in
different compartments just within one
synapse, almost like are you wanting to
sort of look at that granular level or
is it more now taking what you've
learned from this and putting it back
into how can we sort of make the AI more
efficient? Yeah, we are going much more
in this direction now that we see how we
can build this back into AI models.
One has to be a bit careful when using
the free energy principle because it's
such a powerful general framework that
you can apply it to basically anything
and it's not necessarily you will come
up with a useful result in the end.
Just putting this this
started actually as a side project.
This was my kind of COVID pandemic
lockdown project. And I was just curious
about this and whether you can actually
solve this, because I thought the
synopsis is maybe simple enough.
Because when you go into the papers,
they have at some point to go into some
approximations. They do some mean field,
usually, so they go for first modes,
and then you can solve these guys for
more complex, even for neurons, it's
hard, actually, if you go to the neuron
or network level, it's hard. It's very
involved math, but for a sinus is simple
enough, actually. So you can actually do
this and spell everything out if you
make the right assumptions and really
just derive these things. And that was
kind of just kind of
a game I went into and
then it turned out to work quite nicely,
I think, in the end. Yeah.
I'm not sure if you like Mitochondria or
so I'm sure you could apply the same
principles but I'm not sure if the
results you get would be any meaningful
or would help you in any way.
That's always the risk. You invest so
much time and then in the end you get
some results and you don't know. That
was also something that I thought was
quite interesting, which was the synapse
was the agent. It's really easy to
think, oh, we'll make an agent based
model of a neural system. First off,
that tends to not include Glia or non
neural cell types, but it's almost like
a doubly unquestioned assumption that
the cell would be the agent.
But then it was a great transition from
the person throwing the ball over the
wall. That's an action centric approach
where you only have partial visibility
of the consequences and then that
is the exact scenario that the synapse
finds itself in in a different way.
Or it could have been set up so that a
neuron is the agent. We're building
maps, not territories. And so then,
just like you said, free energy
principle, it's a principle for
everything. And so just
making principled statements about
things is table stakes.
And then I guess my question for you is
then what does make it useful or in your
learning and tinkering around with these
models? What differentiated situations
where you applied free energy principle
or active inference and you felt like it
was providing a contribution to your
research direction versus where you
played around and it was like, well,
that was tautological. I think the free
energy principle makes sense in a
context where you have incomplete
information.
So for example, in the synapse case,
right, the question we started with was
this problem that the synapse has to
solve, that it has incomplete
information about the state in the cell
body because it only sees this
kind of or that's the assumption, at
least of the model. And also what we get
from the experimentalists, that it
essentially only sees this back
propagating action potential. So it sees
a single binary variable about the
state of the soma.
So essentially this is a problem of
incomplete information and also the
second ingredient that
you need some form of agency. I think if
you apply the free energy principle to a
system without agency, so if something
is not interacting with an environment
in a closed loop, then it becomes really
sketchy. And I think already this model
is on the edge when it comes because
these models don't really have an
agency, but they at least produce an
output, right? So you can still think of
this as an interaction with an
environment. But as soon as you lose
that, I think then there would be
simpler models that can just give you
the same.
Actually, in the synapse case, the
agency is only this adding noise
actually in the model because the
synapse is triggered presynaptically and
then it uses its internal
state to add the right amount of noise,
which is probably already the minimal
agency you could imagine.
Sir, you want to ask a question or I can
ask a question? Yeah, it was more just a
comment. I think it's quite interesting
people talk about biology. Some people
say it's not a real science because it's
all messy and noisy. But I think it
works really interesting because it's
like you say, the synaptic noise is
actually a reporting of uncertainty. So
in that essence, it's actually probably
quite accurately reporting the messy
world rather than the biology itself
just being all messy. But that's just
what I was thinking about. Yeah, I think
I was curious as well. Like you said,
this was like your Lockdown project,
but I'm just interested in how you sort
of came to use the free energy
principle, how you came across it. Was
it something you were quite familiar
with already or some of your network or
peers were talking about it? Or did you
just stumble across it in a.
Was during my PhD, I was interested in
variational methods and probabilistic
methods. And then I started reading
about this. And so I read a bunch of
Karl Friston's papers and I found this
interesting. And actually,
my PhD supervisor always encouraged
me not to go in that direction.
And then after I finished my PhD and
thought, okay, now I can do what I want,
I try it out.
And then, I guess, do you think it would
be worthwhile, like, next steps for you
or for the field actually trying to
implement this on maybe some of the more
analog chips that are being built in the
space? Like the analog neuromorphic
chips, which I know you can have some
dynamic synapses and things like do you
think it would be worthwhile trying to
implement it on hardware? Or what are
your thoughts on that? I mean, the
triplet rule that comes out from this
first work I showed, I think that would
be interesting to implement it.
The nice feature is that it should, in
principle, should have this self
stabilizing feature because it's really
mimicking the dynamics of
the membrane, of the cell membrane. So
if the neuromorphic hardware would so
if the model in the synapse and the
neuron model match up very well, the
model should give you this nice self
stabilizing feature so that neurons
really not go into some epileptic states
or so. And you get this for free from
this model. That's what we saw in the
simulations, at least. But in
the simulations, of course, we had full
control over this dynamics matching up
in the right way. So that is
probably a bit more tricky for hardware,
but it's probably solvable. So it would
be interesting. What you get for it is
that you have these purely event based
tools which only use pre post spikes,
which is nice. Very cool. Thank you.
Yeah. Daniel, if you had a question?
Well, that's a great principle there,
which is like, if you can design the
neuromorphic algorithm so that it
harnesses a material feature like the
actual leaky permeability of a membrane
or actual spatial proximity, if you can
leverage a material feature,
analog feature that isn't virtualized,
then it's already an adjacency into
future hardware. So that's one great
point. And then to Sarah's point about
almost biology not being a science,
which there is a famous quotation,
there will never be a Newton for a blade
of grass. Because some people say,
yeah, it's a different biology is more
like history. Because whether you
approach this from a development or
ecology or evolution perspective,
biology is a historical science. It's
not like a real science. And then that
reminded me of the cross country shirt
that says, our sport is your punishment.
So it's like, well, no, your noise
is biology's signal. And that's how
it happens. My question was
about this tension between,
I guess, neural and computational ways
of looking at the resources associated
with computation. So from the von
Neumann paradigm. We have a
lot of shared reference points, CPU
cycles, Ram capacity, and all
these kinds of and like, even in your
introductions, you conveyed like, well,
this is how many CPU cycles it's going
through, or this is how many parameters
would have to be stored, or something
like that. However, that's referencing
another paradigm. So what do resource
descriptors or capacity descriptors
look like when we're outside the
space of okay, yeah, power consumption.
That's something that you can put into a
box and just use a bomb calorimeter
that's kind of like a low hanging fruit.
But now okay, beyond just the sheer
energy or caloric requirements, what can
we say that is, like, analogous to the
way that we talk about the processor or
the Ram or the hard drive on a computer?
Yeah, I'd have to think about that one
some more. I do think there was some
interesting comments in the paper on
that slide I showed that talks about the
brain and energy. There was a paper I
linked to. I'll have to get the
reference and let you know what it is
because QR code is gone now. But that
had some interesting ideas, I think, on
what you're getting at there. But I'd
have to defer to the paper.
How do they describe what is being
designed? So they say it has this many
of this type of component, and then that
might do nothing though. So how do they
describe or evaluate these different
designs or algorithms?
I think it's all different depending on
the use case. That's what I've found.
Really? Like, the language is different
depending on if it's written by someone
maybe with more of a neuroscience
background or an engineering background.
And then you kind of get used to some
terms that are more interchangeable than
others. But I do think the terminology
is something which needs to be looked at
a lot more closely in this space,
because then I think that will help
everybody working in it to be on the
same page a little bit closer.
Cool. Well, any other thoughts
or questions? David first and then
Sarah. Also, I'm very curious, what
direction will this series go? But
first, David, what are any other kind of
closing comments or directions you want
to.
Really? I mean, I would say thanks for
having me today. It was really a
pleasure to discuss with you.
Thank you. David, it was amazing to have
you on. I think your work is absolutely
fascinating, and I think it's going to
have lots of benefits in the future for
implementation, which is always nice to
see as well. Yeah. So what was the
question? Where do I see the series
going? Hopefully we can have a new
guest each month. I think it'd be kind
of cool maybe next month to have someone
who's building hardware, so, like,
maybe someone from the BrainScaleS team
or spinnaker team or something like that
would be. Pretty cool, but yeah,
really, I just want to have a space for
people who are interested in this
intersection to meet people and see
talks and reach out to people who are
also working in the space, because it's
pretty niche, but I think it's pretty
important, actually. Having said that,
David, could you let everybody know if
they wanted to reach out to you, what's
the best way for them to do that?
I'm not very active on this discord
channel, so maybe email is still the
best to reach out to me, I guess.
Cool. Do you want to give your oh.
I think my email should be easy
enough to find. But you can also give
the email out there. Sure. Cool. People
can check the papers, and then in the
active inference institute discord,
there's the neuromorphic channel.
All right. Thank you, David and Sarah.
Really cool to see morphstream kick off
its developmental trajectory this way.
So till next time. Thank you.